Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太と
ひびと
栄光の日 生まれの弟･日々人＞
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
＜日本人初の
ﾑｰﾝｳｫｰｶｰとなった日々人は➡
月面での事故の影響による
パニック障害を克服するため➡
To treat the panic disorder that's afflicted him since a lunar accident, Hibito went to Russia.
リハビリの日々を送る｡
一方 日々人の遥か後ろから➡
But now, Mutta is finally one step closer to the moon.
月を目指し始めた六太は
ついに新たな一歩を踏み出す＞
During NEEMO training, he will live in the environment closest to that of the moon,
ニーモ
＜NEEMO訓練｡地球上でもっとも
月面を再現できる海底基地で➡
within a simulated lunar habitat.
ｼﾐｭﾚｰｼｮﾝ生活をするというもの＞
＜死の危険も伴う
油断できない訓練＞
For this training, his life will be in real danger.
＜六太たちに
重い試練がのしかかる！＞
In the coming days, Mutta and the other astronauts will face difficult trials.
なんば
(南波六太)お前…｡
There's something you aren't telling me.
何か隠してるだろ？
その１５歳の娘って➡
Was that fifteen-year-old girl actually a sexy, twenty-something lady?
ホントは２０代の
ｾｸｼｰ美女だったんじゃないのか？
(南波日々人)ちげぇ～よ！
No...
(ゲイツ)⦅おめでとう
今日から君の席だ｡➡
Congratulations.
This will be your office.
自由にしていい⦆
It's all yours...
《別にいらねぇよ…
こんなでかい机》
I don't need such a big desk.
《じっとしてたって
しょうがねぇ 何かしないと》
I won't get anywhere, just sitting around.
I have to do something.
《ロシアでの続きを
やらないとな》
I need to continue that ridiculous-looking training I started in Russia.
《あの一見 馬鹿げた訓練を》
《でも…１人で どうやって…》
But how can I do it alone?
はい｡
Yes?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)やぁ！ヒビト｡
ローリー！
Hey, Hibito!
L-Lowry...
何か 君宛てに
ものすごい荷物が届いたよ｡
There's a huge package for you.
Huh?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)ロシアからだよ｡
It's from Russia.
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)何だろうね？これ｡
What is all this stuff?
なあ ローリー｡
Hey, Lowry...
Hmm?
秘密 守れるか？
Can you keep a secret?
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰ)さて 君たち
宇宙飛行士１２名の➡
I will explain the new training that the twelve astronauts in this room will undergo.
新たな訓練を説明しよう｡
３日後から２週間
ＮＥＥＭＯを実践してもらう｡➡
Beginning in three days, you will be participating in two weeks of NEEMO.
海の底
水深２０メートルに設置された➡
You will live at the bottom of the ocean, in a simulated lunar environment,
仮想月面基地での
シミュレーション生活だ｡➡
twenty meters below sea level.
死の危険も伴う
油断できない訓練だ｡➡
This training requires vigilance, as your lives will be in real danger.
心して取り組むように｡
Prepare yourselves before going in.
《この一歩を踏み出せば➡
With this step, we are now men of the sea.
いよいよ我々も
うみんちゅ
海人の仲間入り！》
《無事に
この海底生活をまっとうし➡
After surviving life at the bottom of the ocean and returning to land,
地上に戻った時には
その誇り高き達成者の証として➡
I'll buy a Sea Diver T-shirt to celebrate.
海人Ｔシャツを買おう！》
アイル ビー バック！
I'll be back.
(新田)また あれやってやがる｡
There he goes again.
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
Having left Houston, we've arrived in Florida.
《私たちは今 ヒューストンを離れ
フロリダ州に来ている》
《小さな島が集まった
キーズ諸島➡
Specifically, in the Florida Keys, a collection of islands.
そこに
４２の橋を架けている道路が➡
Forty-two bridges connect the islands, as part of the Overseas Highway.
オーバーシーズハイウェイ》
このハイウェイ上にある➡
Now the story moves to Key Largo, located on the Highway.
｢キーラーゴ｣という街の近海が
今回の舞台だ》
#81 Worst Enemy
(ﾊﾐﾙﾄﾝ)やあ よく来たね｡
Hey, glad you could make it.
ようこそ アクエリアスツーへ｡
Welcome to Aquarius II.
君たちの
技術支援を任されている➡
I'm Hamilton, the diver who oversees technical support.
ダイバーのハミルトンとは
僕のことだよ｡
あっ どうも 六太です｡
Oh, hello... I'm Mutta.
ワーオ 君の濡れた髪は
実に神秘的だね｡
Wow.
Your wet hair truly is a marvel.
例えるならば…そう
まるで陽光に照らされ➡
I would compare it to that thing which glitters brilliantly in the sunlight...
キラキラとゆらめく
ワカメのような｡
Seaweed.
きっと君は 魚に愛されるよ！
I bet the fish will love you.
ようこそアクエリアスツーへ｡
技術支援を任されている➡
Welcome to Aquarius II.
I'm Hamilton, the diver who oversees technical support.
ダイバーのハミルトンとは
僕のことだよ｡
あっ 真壁ケンジです
よろしく｡
I'm Makabe Kenji. It's a pleasure.
Oh, boy... Two Ants are finally joining us.
やれやれ やっと
｢アンツ｣の お２人が来たか｡
どうやら このメンバーだと➡
Looks like I'll be the leader of this group.
俺が
リーダーということになるな｡
よ よろしくです｡
よろしく ラブさん｡
Nice to meet you.
It's a pleasure, Love.
フン…
お前らのことは よく知ってる｡➡
I've heard a lot about you guys.
特に お前 ナンバムッタ｡➡
Especially you, Nanba Mutta.
アンツの中の
うわさ
はみ出しアリって噂だぜ｡
Sounds like you're considered the lone Ant.
《えっ そんな噂が》
Eh? Who said that?
今じゃ 弟のヒビトも
はみ出し者って話だよな｡
But it sounds like your brother's been hung out to dry...
ハッ 兄弟そろって｡
Both brothers are in trouble.
Huh?
｢アンツ｣って何だい？
What's this Ant business?
こいつら２３期生
｢グループ２３｣の愛称さ｡
It's a nickname for the twenty-third astronaut class, Group 23.
ちまちました奴らだから
｢アリ｣って呼ばれてるのさ｡➡
They got the name because they're scrawny, like ants.
宇宙飛行士は
グループごとに愛称がある｡➡
Astronauts receive nicknames based on their group.
俺たちグループ２２は
｢モンスターズ｣｡
Group 22 was dubbed the Monsters.
まぁ その名がつけられたのは➡
And he's the main reason we got that name.
主に あいつが
原因だろうけどな｡➡
オイ お前もこっち来いよ｡➡
Hey, come over here...
アンディ！
Andy.
《な なるほど…》
Ah...
Makes sense...
《結構な モンスター》
He's quite the monster.
踏みつぶされんようにな
アンツ｡
Make sure you don't get squashed, Ants.
はい…気をつけます｡
Y-Yes... We'll be careful.
《シャロンへ
いよいよ 俺も➡
"Dear Sharon...
I've finally been allowed to start working toward reaching the moon.
月へ向かうことを許されたよ！》
《これから フロリダの海底
２０メートルで➡
I'm about to begin NEEMO in Florida, twenty meters below sea level.
ＮＥＥＭＯと呼ばれる訓練が
始まるんだ》
NEEMO is an acronym for NASA Extreme Environment Mission Operations.
《ＮＥＥＭＯっていうのは➡
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡ極限環境ミッション
運用訓練の略だ》
《舞台は海の中》
We'll train in the ocean.
《アクエリアスっていう
海底の居住施設が３基あって➡
There are three underwater residential facilities called "Aquarius."
それぞれに
１人の支援ダイバーと➡
Each houses one support diver and four astronauts.
４人の宇宙飛行士が入る》
《それで２週間
極限環境を過ごすんだ》
For the next two weeks, we'll be living in extreme conditions.
《問題はチームワーク…》
Teamwork will be key.
《ま ウチの班には
最強の味方➡
Well, Kenji's on my team, and he's the best teammate I could ask for.
ケンジがいるから心強いけど》
シャキーン…｡
《それじゃ…
またメールします》
Anyway, I'll keep writing."
Houston, Texas
こっちです オリビア先生｡
This way, Dr. Olivia.
こんな所でやってるの？
Wait, you're doing it out here?
誰にも知られないようにっていう
ヒビトの希望です｡
Hibito doesn't want anyone to know.
極秘でも やっぱり医師は
必要なんで オリビア先生に｡
We want to keep it secret, but medical expertise is a necessity.
That's why I came to you.
大丈夫 分かってるわ｡
｢３人だけの秘密｣でしょ？
Don't worry, I understand.
I know how to keep a secret.
Yes...
⦅なあ ローリー⦆
Hey, Lowry...
⦅秘密 守れるか？⦆
Can you keep a secret?
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)《パニック障害か…｡➡
A panic disorder, huh?
｢サムライボーイ｣と称えられた
あのタフなヒビトからは➡
Hard to believe, given that Hibito's toughness earned him the "Samurai Boy" nickname...
とても想像できないな～》
《秘密にするのもうなずける
というより…➡
I can see why he'd want to keep it confidential.
I mean...
僕がヒビトだったら 誰１人にも
打ち明けられない気がする》
If I were in Hibito's shoes, I wouldn't tell a soul.
ローリー 始めてくれ！
Lowry, let's start.
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)オーケー！
Right!
このラインまでだよ ヒビト！
Walk to this line, Hibito!
オーケー！
Okay!
The armor is made of heavy material.
《硬い素材でできた胴
プラス 面》
Plus, there's a mask.
《このセットは
結構 宇宙服っぽいぞ…》
It's closer to a spacesuit than you'd think.
《おまけに ちょっと
臭いところも似てるし》
And it smells just as bad.
《でも
これはあくまで剣道着！》
But it's only kendo gear.
楽しく行こう｡
I can enjoy myself.
ワーオ！ジャパニーズ ケンドー！
カッコいい～！
Whoa!
Japanese kendo! Cool!
ロシア式訓練 再開！
Back to Russian training!
(ジム)こちら ｼﾞｮﾝｿﾝｽﾍﾟｰｽｾﾝﾀｰ
ＮＥＥＭＯ管制室｡➡
This is Johnson Space Center, NEEMO Control.
今日の訓練は ローバーの
遠隔操作テストを午前中に➡
We will spend the morning testing remotely controlled rovers.
午後からは 船外に出て
月の重力設定をした➡
In the afternoon, you'll head out in spacesuits to perform a center of gravity check and an operational check.
宇宙服での重心確認
および 動作確認テストだ｡
彼らには知らせていない
この訓練の目的があります｡➡
We have not told the astronauts the purpose of this training.
アクエリアスワンから
スリーまで➡
Each Aquarius module houses two veteran astronauts
それぞれに
ベテラン飛行士が２人と➡
新人飛行士を
２人ずつ配置しています｡
and two rookie astronauts.
私なりに 彼らの人間性を
見極めた上で➡
I selected these teams, based on my evaluation of their personalities.
このチーム編成に
至ったわけですが｡➡
各チーム２人いる新人のうち➡
One of the two new astronauts in each group will be chosen.
どちから１人を
選ぶことになります｡➡
Only one per pair will be able to go to the moon.
月へ行くことが出来るのは
どちらか１人だけ｡
つまり
彼らはパートナーに見えて➡
In other words, they may seem to be partners...
実は 一番の敵です｡
But in reality, they are each other's worst enemy.
目の前に広がるのは
ディープブルーの未知なる世界｡➡
Before you lies an unexplored world of deep blue.
魅せられるよねぇ～➡
An entrancing sight, yes?
The best aquarium you could ask for.
なんて ぜいたくな
水槽だろうねぇ｡➡
この壮大なスケール
ファンタスティック！
It's just massive! Fantastic!
《うう～ん》
ごらんよ フエダイの群れだよ｡
かわいいね～！
Look... There's a school of snapper.
Aren't they cute?
(ケンジ)ホントだ｡
Oh... It's true.
きっと 君たち宇宙飛行士を
歓迎してくれてるんだろうねぇ｡
I'm sure they're here to welcome you astronauts!
｢ようこチョ ボクラの海へ！｣
とか言って｡
They're saying, "Welcome to the ocean!"
あ フンしたね 今｡
Ah, I think one just pooped.
《あ…》
Yeah.
いやぁ～ 神秘だよねぇ 海は｡
Yes, the ocean is full of wonders!
海が好きなんだね ハミルトンは｡
You really love the ocean, don't you, Hamilton?
Eh, you can tell?
えっ わかるかい？
《わかるよ そりゃ》
It's totally obvious!
そうだねぇ➡
Indeed...
もし｢１つだけ願いを叶えていい｣
って言われたら➡
If I could have one wish,
ボクは｢エラ呼吸の能力と
背ビレが欲しい｣って言うね｡➡
I would want gills and a dorsal fin.
もう この願いが叶うんなら
ボクは他に何もいらないよ～｡
《２つだし！》
If that wish were granted, I wouldn't ask for anything else.
That's two wishes.
Hey.
(ラブ)おい 早く着替えろアンツ
船外訓練が始まるぞ｡
Get changed, Ants.
We're going to train outside.
はい｡
Ah...
Yes.
知ってんな？これ｡➡
You know what these are?
ＮＥＥＭＯで
使用する潜水マスクだ｡
They're NEEMO diving helmets.
潜水中に この中に水が
浸入してきた時の対処法は➡
If water starts seeping in, do you know what to do?
わかってんだろうな？
We'll be fine, Love.
大丈夫だよ ラブさん
事前講習 受けたから｡
We went through orientation.
Oh, really?
ハッ そうかい｡
H-Hey...
おおっと…え？
Did I bump you?
今 お前にぶつかったか？
まさか…｡
Of course not...
Well, to be honest... You did kind of bump into me...
いや まあ 正直に言うと
ぶつかったけど…｡
ちょんってね｡
そうか 悪いな｡
A little.
Ah, sorry...
これからの分も
先に謝っておく｡
Let me apologize now for any future bumps.
Huh?
俺 デカイから➡
I'm big, so I bump into stuff a lot.
しょっちゅう何かに
ぶつかるんでな｡
《なるほど…》
Makes sense...
チームツー
ジョージ･ラブ 潜水開始！➡
Team 2, George Love, diving in!
続いて アンディ･タイラー｡
Next up is Andy Tyler.
さあ 君たちもディープブルーに
飛び込んでおいで～！
Okay, it's your turn to jump into the deep blue!
Yeah!
う…ハミルトン 何？そのキズ｡
Hamilton, what's that scar?
ああ これかい？
Ah, this?
そうだねぇ 一応 ムッタたちも
気をつけた方がいいね｡
Oh, right... You should probably be careful.
やさしい海も 時として➡
At times, the gentle sea can be vicious.
気まぐれに牙を剥くんだよ｡
《海中での要注意事項 その１！》
Underwater precaution #1!
《ホースや体が岩場などに
ひっかかっても！》
If your suit or any hoses are caught on rocks...
《決して慌ててはならない！》
Never panic!
《水中拘束によって
パニックを起こし➡
Seeing new divers, stuck underwater, panic and get themselves killed is common.
それが事故死につながることが
初心者ダイバーによくある》
《要注意事項 その２！》
Precaution #2!
《もし 不測の事態が
起きたとしても！》
If something unexpected happens...
Do not head for the surface!
《急浮上してはならない！》
おちい
《これは パニックに陥ると
起こしやすいミスだ》
A common mistake when a diver panics
《水面に出れば
助かると思い 急浮上すると➡
is to make for the surface, for help.
水圧の変化により
肺が破裂し 最悪 死に至る》
The pressure changes can cause your lungs to burst.
And in extreme cases, you can die.
Precaution #3!
《要注意事項 その３！》
《エイに注意！》
Beware of stingrays!
《エイは毒とげを持っているので
かなり危険》
Stingrays have poisonous stingers, so they can be dangerous.
《海底の砂に身を潜めている
エイを知らずに踏んでしまい➡
They tend to hide under sand on the ocean floor,
毒とげに刺される被害は多い！》
so people accidentally step on them and get stung.
《激痛 局所貧血症｡➡
Victims suffer from pain, local anemia, and difficulty breathing due to shock.
ショックによる呼吸困難などの
症状を引き起こす》
《いやまったく…
海は神秘だよなぁ ハミルトン》
Yeah, the sea sure is full of wonders, Hamilton.
Nanba Mutta...
(バトラー)ナンバ ムッタ…｡
あの男が…｡
I didn't expect him...
⦅バーティカルクライムロール！
レッツゴー!!⦆
Vertical climb roll!
Let's go!
あれを…やるとはなぁ｡
...to pull that off.
《チャンスは作ってやった》
I've given him a chance.
《あとは
ＮＥＥＭＯでの評価次第…➡
It all depends on his NEEMO performance.
ＮＥＥＭＯは
最も本番に近い訓練｡➡
NEEMO training is as close to the real thing as you can get.
ここで あの
ﾊﾞｰﾃｨｶﾙｸﾗｲﾑﾛｰﾙのような➡
If he shows the skill and determination he displayed with the vertical climb roll,
技術と意志を
見せてくれるのなら➡
月への切符を渡すことに
もうためらいはない》
I will have no qualms sending him to the moon.
《だが｢リーダーシップ｣｢知識量｣
｢行動力･判断力｣全てにおいて➡
However,
when it comes to leadership, knowledge, initiative, and decision-making,
まだまだマカベ･ケンジの方が
評価は高いようだな…》
Makabe Kenji still outperforms him.
ハッハハハ！動きが変だよ｡➡
Your movements are so strange...
危ない危ない ハハッ ムッ君｡
Be more careful,
Mu!
おわっとと…｡
なるほど ハハハ…｡
I see...
月の低重力でも
トリプルアクセルはムリだな｡
I guess even with the moon's lower gravity, I still can't do a triple axel.
さては
日々人君のムーンジャンプに➡
Trying to come up with something to rival Hibito's moon jump, Mu?
対抗しようとしてるね ムッ君｡
Well...
《バレたか》
How'd he know?
《シャロン 今日は
潜水服を重りで調節して➡
"Sharon...
Today, we experienced the moon's gravity, using specially calibrated diving suits.
月の重力を体験したよ》
《徒歩に始まり
石拾いの動作や起き上がり➡
We were asked to walk, pick up rocks, and stand up.
それから ハシゴの上り下り
な～んて動作を➡
Then we climbed up and down ladders for a while...
ひたすらやったよ》
《他にも いろんな 動きを
試して 月重力にも慣れたし➡
Additionally, we were able to try various other kinds of movement.
I've become accustomed to lunar gravity,
明日からが また楽しみだよ》
and I can't wait for tomorrow."
明日からの訓練の２割は
今日と同じようなものだ｡➡
Starting tomorrow, twenty percent of the training will be similar to what you've already done.
残りの８割は 他チームと
競い合う形式となってくる｡
While the remaining eighty percent will be competition against the other teams.
この意味 わかるな？
I'm sure you can guess what that means.
チームの評価は そのまま➡
The team evaluation determines who will be assigned to lunar missions first.
月ミッションのアサイン順に
つながる可能性が高い｡
つまり
他のチームには負けられない｡
In other words, we must beat the other teams.
足を引っ張んじゃねぇぞ
アンツ｡
Don't ruin this for us, Ants.
《引っ張りそう…》
I might screw it up.
(コン コン)
で でけっ…｡
I-It's huge.
(ﾊﾐﾙﾄﾝ)出たね バラクーダだよ｡
That's a barracuda.
彼らには要注意だよ｡
Use extra caution around them...
｢サメより恐ろしい｣って
言う人もいるぐらいだ｡
Some say that they're scarier than sharks.
人を襲うことは まれだけど
あなどると こうなる｡
It's rare for one to attack a human.
But if you aren't careful, here's what happens.
However, I still like them.
だけど
僕は彼らが好きなんだ｡
バラクーダの大群の雄大さには
いつも目を奪われるよ｡
I never can look away from the magnificence of a large school of barracuda.
《こ こんな怖ぇ奴らが
大群で現れたら➡
I-If a large school appeared, could I stay calm?
俺は ちびらずに
いられるだろうか？》
《いや 無理そう…》
No, probably not...
(ジム)おはよう 諸君｡
Good morning, gentlemen.
It's your second day of NEEMO.
ＮＥＥＭＯ ２日目だ
準備はいいか？
Ready to go?
グッモーニング ケンジ｡
Good morning, Kenji.
カペ｡
Roo-ra!
それでは 課題を説明する｡
I will now announce your next task.
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#82 Space Family
We're training on the bottom of the ocean.
＜海の底での訓練生活｡
やっぱり ケンジとのコンビは➡
It's a lot easier with Kenji around!
やりやすいぜ＞
(ケンジ)＜ホントだね ムッ君｡➡
You've got it, Mu...
Together, we can do anything!
２人でなら 何だってできそうだ＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Space Family"
＜ハッ まったく
おめでたい奴らだな お前らは＞
You guys really are too relaxed.